Guide to the American Association of University Professors, University of Montana Chapter Records 1930-1977
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
American Association of University Professors, University of Montana Chapter records
1930-1977
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 654
American Association of University Professors, University of Montana Chapter
0.6 linear feet
This collection includes meeting minutes, correspondence and newsletters of the University of Montana-Missoula's chapter of the American Association of University Professors. The majority of the material is from the 1940s to the 1960s.
Historical Note
John Hopkins’ Professor Arthur O. Lovejoy and John Dewey formed the American Association of University Professors (AAUP) in 1915 to protect the "academic freedom” of college professors nationwide. It is not clear when the Montana chapter of the AAUP was established but it likely began on the University of Montana campus in the late 1910s. The first minute book in this collection dates from 1930. The National AAUP’s concern for the wellbeing and academic freedom of professors brought the organization’s attention to UM on a number of occasions, including during the dismissal of President Craighead in 1915 and during the controversy over the discharge of Librarian Philip Keeney in 1937. They also participated in preparing and moving a collective bargaining bill through the Montana legislature in the mid-1970s.
This collection contains memos to faculty members, 1942-1977, salary studies, 1951-1960, minutes and organizational materials, 1930-1962, and newsletters, 1965-1974, for the Montana chapter of the American Association of University Professors.
This collection is arranged alphabetically and then chronologically.
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
The custodial history of this collection is unknown.
The material in this collection was originally filed with the Mansfield Library's University Publications (UPUBa) collection. It was processed as a manuscript collection n 2002.
A small amount of material about the AAUP in Montana can be found in RG 01, Office of the President of the University of Montana.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
American Association of University Professors. University of Montana Chapter. Archives.; University of Montana (Missoula, Mont.: 1965-1994)--Faculty.; Montana State University (Missoula, Mont.)--Faculty.
College teacher--Montana--Missoula
Colleges and Universities; Montana
- Correspondence, memos to faculty, 1942-1964 (Box-folder 1/1)
- Correspondence, memos to faculty, 1966-1977 (Box-folder 1/2)
- Financial Records, salary studies, 1951-1960 (Box-folder 1/3)
- Minutes, 1930-1948 (Box-folder 1/4)
- Minutes, 1949-1955 (Box-folder 1/5)
- Minutes, 1955-1962 (Box-folder 2/1)
- Organization, 1962, n.d. (Box-folder 2/2)
- Organization, principles, 1940, 1953 and 1959 (Box-folder 2/3)
- Speeches and Writings, Neils Report, 1958 (Box-folder 2/4)
- Speeches and Writings, newsletter, 1965-1974 (Box-folder 2/5)